Let's see if we can use the histograms then, to basically, estimate a noise.
让我们来看看 我们是否可以用直方图来估计噪声
We need to estimate both the shape of the noise,
我们需要估计噪声的形状
basically the function of the noise. Its Gaussian is uniform, its salt and
也就是噪声的方程 它到底是高斯噪声 还是均匀分布噪声 又或是椒盐噪声
pepper. And once we estimate that, we need to
一旦我们估计出了方程 我们还需要
estimate actually the parameters of that. So, we're going to use the same image
估算它的实际参数 接下来我们将要使用大家之前见过的
that we have seen before. This very simple image.
这张图像 这张很简单的图像
And let's assume for a moment that you manage to go into a region that has only,
然后假设我们已经获取到一个区域
in the original image, only one type of pixel value.
这个在原图像中的区域 只有一种像素值
So, one gray value for all the pixels there in the original image.
原图像中的这个区域只有一个灰度值
And we see that illustrated here. If we manage to do that, then we go and
正如这里展示的 如果我们获得了这个区域 接下来
plot the histogram. The distribution of pixel values for that
就可以画出它的直方图 也就是这个区域像素值的分布
region. For example, this would be the
例如 这就是
distribution of the pixel values. Now, when we see these, basically we can
像素值的分布 现在当我们看到这个分布 我们可以
immediately guess what kind of noise is here.
很快地猜出来这个地方的噪声类型是什么
So, I'm going to ask you, what type of noise was added to this region that would
那么我来问问大家 这个区域是加了什么样的噪声
give us this histogram check?" It's very easy to see that basically, this is a
导致我们看到这种直方图? 这应该是很容易看出来的
Gaussian noise. We are now experts.
这是一个高斯噪声 我们现在已经是专家啦
So, the moment we see the, this, we immediately recognize it.
当我们看到这个图的时候 我们马上就认出它了
Now, that we know that it's Gaussian, basically we need to estimate the average
现在我们知道它是高斯噪声 我们需要估计它的平均值和它的方差
and the variance and that's very easily done by just computing it from the pixel
这个只需要从像素值来简单计算一下就可以了
values. Maybe it was really noise, as here, that
也许这里加入的是瑞利噪声 如此图所示
was added. If that's the case, we once again use the
如果是那样的话 我们再一次使用
histogram distribution to basically decide and compute the average and the
直方图分布来确定和计算平均值和方差
variance. And with that, we can try to invert it as
有了这些 我们就可以尝试
we're going to discuss in a few minutes. Here, again, we're complete experts now
用我们接下来要讨论的方法把它转换回来 现在 我们已经完全是噪声专家了
in noise. So, it's very clear that was basically
很明显 这里这个区域
uniform noise added to that region. And once again, we can variously
加的是均匀噪声 再一次地 我们可以
estimate, basically, the region of the noise, where the uniform noise was added.
很简单地估算这个被加入了均匀噪声的区域的噪声
And what's actually the value that was added or the probability of those values.
和加入噪声的具体数值 或者那些值的概率
Now, what happens if we don't know it, know, don't know the type of noise?
但是 如果我们不知道噪声的类型又怎么办呢?
Then, it's very easy. Let's assume that this is the
实际上这个也很简单 让我们假设 这个就是
distribution that we observe. So, we can go and try.
我们观察到的分布 那么让我们来尝试一下
We try Gaussian and we fit the best possible Gaussian to this distribution.
我们先试试高斯分布 找与这个分布最匹配的高斯分布
We tried [UNKNOWN] we try gamma, we try uniform.
再试瑞利分布 再试伽马分布 或者均匀分布
We, we basically go and fit using standard tools for function fitting.
我们就这样使用这些标准工具来做函数拟合
We basically fit the best of each one of the distributions.
我们找到每个分布类型中与这个分布最匹配的参数
And the one that produces the smallest error, that's the one that we pick.
哪一个产生的误差最小 我们就选择哪一个
Maybe that was in the original distribution of the noise but hopefully,
虽然有可能并不是原来的噪声分布 但是我们希望
that's a good enough approximation for that noise.
这是一个对噪声的较好近似
So, this is the way that we can estimate noise if we find a region that has
如果我们可以找到一个原本有着相同像素值的区域
basically uniform original pixel values. If not, we're going to have to work a bit
我们就可以这样来估计噪声 否则 我们就要多做一些工作
more. So, first of all, people try to do that
首先 我们可以尝试
with relatively small regions. If you have a small region, you have a
相对较小的区域 如果我们有一个比较小的区域 那么
larger probability that you are picking uniform regions.
就有更大的可能性选中一个均一的区域
The problem with small regions is you don't have enough pixel values to
小区域有一个问题 就是我们没有足够的像素值
estimate your averages and your standard deviations or your balances.
来估计平均值和标准差或者方差
For example if I pick a region with only one pixel, I won't be able to estimate
例如 如果我选择一块只有一个像素点的区域
any statistics on the noise from from that pixel.
就无法从这个像素点中估计出任何噪声的统计信息
If you pick too large of a region, you have the risk that you're basically
如果我们选择了太大的区域 可能会选取到
getting into very distinct pixel values in the original image, two or more.
原图像中像素值变化很大的部分 可能有两种或以上的像素值
And then, what will happen here? We already know.
这样的话又会如何呢? 我们已经知道了
We actually are going to have histograms that look like this.
我们实际上会得到一个看起来像这样的直方图
Basically, have two peaks. If that happens, then there are
它有着两个峰值 如果是这样
techniques to try to detect that there is more than one peak in the histogram.
我们也有方法来检测到 直方图中不只一个峰值
And if that happens, basically either you make the region smaller, or you separate
如果这种情况发生了 可以把区域缩小 或者
the histogram, and then you do an estimate for each one of the regions
分离直方图 然后再对每一个区域分别估计
independently. The other thing to be very careful is
另一件需要小心的事是
that you might need to do this type of estimates in every region in the image.
我们很可能需要对图像中的每一个区域都做这样的估计
Because nothing guarantees unless you know that in advance the noise is the
因为 除非我们事先知道这些噪声是均匀噪声
uniform noise, is the same all around. If it's the same all around, then you can
否则我们无法保证噪声的一致 如果全图都是同样的噪声 那么我们可以
just go and pick a number of regions in the image,
在图中只选取一部分区域
do your estimates for example, average all the estimates.
来做我们的估计 例如 把所有的估计值都平均一下
So, you compute the mean and standard deviation of variants for each one of the
我们对每一个区域都计算出平均值、标准差以及方差
regions. And then you say, hey, my noise is this
然后我们就说 这个噪声是
distribution. But I'm going to average all the means
这样一个分布 我们算出所有平均值的平均
that I computed, I'm going to average all the variances I
算出所有方差的平均值
computed, and that's going to be my estimate.
我们把这个平均作为我们的估计
So, these are the standard ways of computing the noise from your image.
这就是从图像中计算噪声的标准方法
Now, why is this very useful? As we say in the very beginning, our
为什么说这个非常有用呢？ 我们最开始讲过
model here, and I'm going to remove for a second the
我们的模型 暂时不考虑
deterioration part of the image. I'm going to assume there is just noise.
图像中的退化部分 我们假设现在只有噪声
We say f of x,y is basically my original image and the noise was added.
我们让 g(x, y) 等于原来的图像加上噪声
Now, once I estimate the parameters of my noise and the type of my noise with
现在 一旦我们估计出了噪声的参数和噪声的类型
experience, for example, I know what kinds of filters work well for different
根据经验 例如我知道什么样的滤波器
types of noise. For example, for Gaussian filtering, we
对不同的噪声有效 比如对于高斯噪声的过滤
already saw the average filter, basically the mean filter and also the non-local
我们已经看到过均值滤波器 包括均值滤波器和非局部平均滤波
means. That if we manage to cut your regions,
如果我们能够切出一块区域
that if there uniform or similar across the image, then averaging is great.
其中的像素值是相同或者相似的 那么平均的效果会很好
If I have a pixel distribution, let's say, around zero, averaging would
如果我们得到的是一个像素的分布 比如说在0附近
basically almost get rid of, of that noise.
平均也能几乎完全去除那种噪声
The same for uniform noise. So, depending on the noise type, we
均匀分布噪声也是一样的 所以 根据噪声的类型
basically can use different filters. Salt and pepper noise.
我们可以使用不同的滤波器 而对于椒盐噪声
Medium filter is a great filter for salt and pepper noise.
中值滤波器对椒盐噪声来说是很好的滤波器
We know that salt and pepper are kind of isolated.
我们知道椒盐噪声从某种意义上来讲是孤立的
We actually saw an example in the previous week.
我们在前一周里看过它的一个例子
They are isolated points and, basically, when we compute the medium, we just
它们是一些孤立的点 当我们算出中值
basically eliminate those isolated points and end up replacing them by the pixel
我们就能消除这些孤立的像素 最终把它们替换成周围点的
values around them. So, knowing the type of noise help us to
像素值 所以知道了噪声的类型会帮助我们
basically design and decide which type of filters, which types of operations, are
设计和决定使用哪种滤波器 哪种操作 可以用来
we going to do to be able to recover the original image from the basically
从掺入了噪声的图片中
decorated from the noisy image. We're going to see in a few weeks, when
重建出原始图像来 我们将会在以后几周看到
we go to more advanced techniques, that also knowing the type of noise can
在我们讲解更多的高级技术之后 知道了噪声的类型
basically enter the design of the algorithm in a completely different
还能帮助我们以完全不同的方式来设计算法
fashion. For example, if we are going to basically
例如 如果我们知道
know that we are dealing with Gaussian noise,
我们要处理高斯噪声
remember, we're tying to get an estimate, F,
提醒一下 我们要尝试获得一个F的估计
that is very similar, or as similar as possible to the original one.
它要跟原图像非常相似或者尽可能相似
If we know that the noise is Gaussian, we're also going to basically constrain
如果我们知道这是高斯噪声 我们将把它约束在
the, this is g, I apologize for that,
这个是 g 不好意思
this is g. So, for a Gaussian noise,
这个是 g 那么 对于高斯噪声
the error between these two has to behave as Gaussian noise,
它们两个之间的误差就得是一个高斯噪声
okay? So, this is my estimate, my denoise
好的 这是我的估计 我的无噪图像
image. This is my noisy image, what I observe,
这个是我们能看到的 有噪声的图像
this should be as close as possible to the original image.
这个必须跟原始图像尽可能地接近
Let's assume it's identical to the original image.
让我们假设它跟原始图像是一样的
Then, the difference between these two should have a Gaussian distribution.
那么它们两个之间的差异就是一个高斯分布
So, I expect my noise to have a Gaussian distribution, and we are going to see
我预期这个噪声有一个高斯分布 我们将会看到
that we can impose that by basically imposing some properties on the mean
我们可以得到均方误差的一些性质
square error, basically the error squared, or the difference between my
也就是误差的平方 或者说实际图像和估计图像的差 的一些性质
observe and my estimated image. Now, if my, basically, noise was
现在 如果我们的噪声被估计为
estimated to be uniform, then I'm going to have to impose here a
均匀分布 将会得到一个不同的误差
different error. For example, we are going to see that if
例如 我们将会看到
the nose, the noise, sorry, is exponential,
如果这个噪声是指数噪声
what we are going to try to do is my estimate minus my observation, but
我们就可以试着用估计值减去实际值
without this square. That's why we're going to try to measure
但是不需要取平方 这就是为什么我们要测定和确认
and make sure that that basically behaves in the way I expect from an exponential
这些误差的表现 与我期望的指数噪声一致
noise. So, once again, the key concept is if you
那么我再强调一次 这里的核心思想是
know denoise, then you know that your estimate minus your observation has to
如果我们知道了噪声分布 那么估计值减去观察值
behave like that noise. So, if I,
这个差应该跟已知噪声的分布一致 所以如果我们
no, my noise is uniform and I compute my estimate and my estimate.
已经知道这个噪声是均匀分布的 而且计算出了估计值 我们这个估计
minus the observation gives me a Gaussian distribution,
减去实际的观察值 所得到的却是高斯分布
I say, okay, I made two possibile mistakes here,
那我就说 好吧 我这里可能有两种错误
Either I estimated wrong my noise or I basically did the wrong denoising because
要么我对噪声的估计是错的 要么我的去噪是错的
I didn't get back what I assume was the type of noise.
因为我没有得回我假设的噪声类型
And this is how you basically you put back your noise estimates into your
这就是我们如何将噪声估计应用到
design of image restoration techniques. Once again, something that we didn't see
图像复原技术的设计上的 再强调一次 这里并不会
in image enhancement but we actually can see an image restoration.
看到图像增强 但是我们还是可以看得到图像复原
We push it back to design off the filter or to basically select parameters of the
我们将其应用到滤波器的设计 或者只是选择滤波器的参数
filter. Of course, if I have more noise, more
当然 如果我们有更多的噪声 更多的
salt and pepper noise, I might need to decide on the size of my medium filter
椒盐噪声 我有可能需要确定中值滤波器的
window in a different fashion than if I have less noise.
窗口大小 使用的方法跟噪声较少的时候相比有所不同
So, this is how you basically, once again, put, put back that information
那么 这就是我们如何将这些信息应用到
into the design. We have talked a lot about this, but
设计中的 关于这点我们已经讲了很多
remember, the original model have here the h function,
但是请记住一点 原始模型中 这里还有一个 H函数
the degradation function. So, let's just spend, in the next video,
也就是退化函数 那么 让我们在下一次的视频中
sometime discussing it. Thank you very much.
再花一点时间讨论它 感谢大家 //果壳教育无边界字幕组 | ctzsm | 冰之冷 | 某音某莹